Blandy, Tom; Papers apap133
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Tom Blandy Papers
1980-1999
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap133
1.16 cubic ft.
The Tom Blandy Papers document the group Concerned Citizens for the Environment's legal and political opposition to the proposed Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Tom Blandy in May 2002.
Biographical Sketch
Tom Blandy, a resident of Troy, New York, is an architect whose specialty is adaptive reuse of older buildings. He has been involved with a number of local and regional environmental groups, including the Rensselaer County Greens, Save the Pine Bush, and Concerned Citizens for the Environment (CCE). CCE was formed in 1987 by Ken Dufty as a means of opposing the Inter-Power coal burning power generation plant proposed for Halfmoon, New York. Dufty left in the early 1990s to form the Rensselaer County Environmental Management Council and Tom Blandy became president of the CCE at that time.
During the late 1990s, CCE was primarily concerned with the Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator proposed by the American Ref-Fuel Company. Ref-Fuel was a joint operation of Brown Ferris Industries & Air Products & Chemical Inc. The opposition campaign culminated in the court case Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation & American Ref-Fuel Company. CCE charged that the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation had incorrectly issued a permit for the building of a solid waste transfer station, which included the proposed incinerator. CCE won the initial trial in 1996, but lost the appeal in 1997.
Scope and Contents
These papers document the political and legal opposition of the group Concerned Citizens for the Environment against the proposed Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator. They consist of court records, correspondence, documentary evidence, publications, news clippings, and other materials directly or indirectly relating to this opposition. The most well documented aspect is the case Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation & American Ref-Fuel Company, which contains official court documents, legal briefs, and correspondence with CCE's law firm, Gordon, Siegel, Mastro, Mullaney, Gordon & Galvin, P.C.
This collection does not contain a great deal of administrative information about CCE itself. What there is consists of correspondence, meeting minutes, and newsletters, primarily focused on the trial and related fundraising attempts. These materials, along with collections of materials indirectly related to the incinerator, make up the Subject File series. There is no biographical information about Tom Blandy himself, though there is an autographed copy of his book on home weatherproofing, All Through the House.
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the subject guide for Conservation and the Environment. Of particular interest are the records of Bethlehem Work on Waste (APAP-148), another group that opposed the incinerator.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1: Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator, 1991-1998, Undated
Series 2: Subject Files, 1990-1999, Undated
Both series are arranged alphabetically.
Rensselaer County, New York; Conservation and the Environment; Ecology- New York; Environmental Law; Incinerators; Refuse and Refuse Disposal- Law and Legislation; Green Island (N.Y.); Agendas (administrative records); Articles; Diagrams; Fliers (printed matter); Legal documents; Maps; Minutes; Newsletters; Notes; Photographs; Posters; Blandy, Tom; Concerned Citizens for the Environment; American Ref-Fuel Company; New York (State) Department of Environmental Conservation
- Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator, 1991-1998; Undated; 1; .66 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials pertaining to the solid waste incinerator proposed by American Ref-Fuel Company in the town of Green Island, New York. The bulk of the series consists of documents relating to the case Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation & American Ref-Fuel Company, in which CCE charged the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation with improperly issuing a permit for the incinerator. These documents are primarily court documents from the case and the resulting appeals, but also include correspondence with the law firm representing CCE. The remainder of the series consists of background materials for the case and publicity materials opposing the incinerator.
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, Appeal, Correspondence, Court Documents, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, Appeal, Legal Briefs, Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, Counter Appeal, Court Demands, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, Cross Appeal, Correspondence, Court Documents, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, Initial Trial, Court Demands, Decision, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment vs. New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, Legal Bills, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Doctors' Fundraising Packet, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator, Articles, Fliers, 1992-1995; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator, Correspondence, 1992-1995; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator, Diagrams, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator, Newspaper Clippings, 1991-1995; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Green Island Solid Waste Incinerator, Notes, 1991-1994; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New York Public Interest Research Group Legal File on Green Island Transfer Station, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - New York Public Interest Research Group Legal File on Green Island Transfer Station, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - New York Public Interest Research Group Legal File on Green Island Transfer Station, Documents Obtained through FOIL, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Troy Area United Ministries (TAUM), Correspondence, Meeting Minutes, Fliers, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "The Very Real Danger," Book, Poster, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Subject Files, 1980-1999; Undated; 2; .5 cubic ft.
  These files contain materials relating to solid waste and incineration issues, such as recycling and dioxin production. The series also contains the small amount of administrative materials for the group Concerned Citizens for the Environment (CCE) to be found in this collection. It also contains materials relating to the proposed Inter-Power power generation facility that inspired Ken Dufty to form CCE in opposition.
  - All Through the House: A Guide to Home Weatherization by Thomas Blandy and Denis Lamoureux, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Citizen's Clearinghouse for Hazardous Waste, Conference Materials, 1990; 1992; 1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment, Correspondence, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment, Meeting Minutes, Agendas, Notes, 1996-1997; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Concerned Citizens for the Environment, Newsletters, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dioxins, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Inter-Power Facility, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mount Ida Preservation Association, Poestenkill Dam, Correspondence, Maps, Pictures, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, 1989; 1993-1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, Correspondence for Citizens' Environmental Coalition, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Recycling, 1992-1996; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ref-Fuel, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ref-Fuel, Cumberland Farms vs. Browning Ferris Industries, Court Documents, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Solid Waste Incineration, 1991-1995; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Toxic Dumps in New York State, Map, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)